BioCatalogue focus group meeting Nov 27 2009

Attending

Ben, Olivier, Chrysanthi, Franck

Apologies

Duncan, Marco

Minutes

Introduction

BioCatalogue is a curated registry of Life science services
Some challenges:

loads of web services using different technology (SOAP, REST)

different standard available

get users and provider to annotate web services

The role of the Focus Group is to discuss the issues and propose some solutions. In addition the Focus Group provides feedback on the BioCatalogue products.

Discussion

1-Web service annotation in Life Science

Use of controlled vocabulary

Service categorization

Tag on service/operations/ inputs/outputs

Annotation quality matrix

2-Community/provider involvements - How To

Find different ways to add annotation to web service e.g through API

Possibility to import annotation from application using webs services such as Taverna, myExperiment etc.

Service providers or users should gain something in return. For example report the result of service testing to the provider.

3-What do you expect from the BioCatalogue?

An API to ease the deployment of services; possibility to do everything through the API (service and annotation submission, service testing and monitoring etc…).

Integration with other tools consuming web service such as Taverna, myExperiment etc…

Link between inputs and outputs of services

Monitor submitter contact details. With time, some of them will be out of date. For example when a service submitter leaves his project.

Define policy for service which have been offline for a long period of time

BioCatalogue is serving 2 different communities; it should be clear from the site

Community 1 knows what web services are and wants to use them

Community 2 wants to know more about web services.

Possibility to rank search result based on service availability test.

Possibility to test web service from the BioCatalogue

Make it easy for user of the BioCatalogue to contact service provider

How do you know that the service is well annotated? Need a kind of BioCatalogue approved annotation stamp.

Action

Franck to create a mailing list for the focus group

Event

BioCatalogue annotation jamboree in Manchester Nov 27

Versioning Policy

The catalogue requires a mechanism for users to find out the details of a service (and its annoation) at a particular time point. This is akin to the versioning methods in in source control systems (e.g. CVS, Subversion, etc.) and in wiki systems. However there are potential issues with the granularity of versioning, the complexity of versioning visible to the user and clarity of conflicts between versions from different sources.

Service Version

Where a service description document is supplied we in effect have service details and annotations from the service provider. If we assume that changes to the service description document indicate changes to the service, then the service document can be used as a method to produce a “service version”, which is incremented for each change to the service document. To be able to reconstruct the service document at a particlar point in time, the catalogue will have to cache the document in some way, and provide an appropriate way to vide the changes.

For services without a service description document, the versioning model above would not apply, although a similar technique could be used in cases where a documentation URL is available.

Community/Curator Annotation Version

It is expected that the community/curator produced annotation will change faster than the provider supplied annotations. It is also expected that in some cases revisions to the service and the provider supplied annotations will invalidate or conflict with these annotations. Thus we need to be able to track these annotations independantly of the service itself, and highlight potential issues when they arise.

Two Version Model

This suggests that each service will have two versions in the catalogue:

Service version: based on service desription documents or documentation from the service provider

Annotation Version: tracking of the additional annotations provided by the BioCatalogue curators and community

This is akin to the versioning model in the sequence databases, where there is a sequence version which refers solely to the sequence itself and an entry or annotation version which refers to the annotation attached to the sequence. The classic example of this is UniProtKB (see UniSave for details).

However the use of two version numbers can be very confusing for users, one possible solution is to use a combined version number similar to that used for software where the major version is used for the service and the minor number for the annotation. For example: for service version 2 and annotation version 10 we could have the simpler 2.10 as the version displayed.

The BioCatalogue Core Team

Carole Goble: Project lead, Manchester.

Rodrigo Lopez: Project lead, EBI.

Hamish McWilliam: Service manager, EBI.

Thomas Laurent: Software engineer, EBI.

Eric Nzuobontane: Software engineer, EBI.

Jiten Bhagat: Software engineer, Manchester.

Franck Tanoh: Bioinformatician and curator, Manchester.

Katy Wolstencroft: Bioinformatician, Manchester.

Our Advisory Board

The BioCatalogue Strategic advisory board members are:

Professor Chris Rawlings, Rothamsted Research, UK, Bioinformatics.

Professor Anil Wipat, Newcastle upon Tyne, UK, Bioinformatics.

Dr Jo Dicks, John Innes Centre, UK, Computational and Systems Biology.

Dr Robert Gill, Pronota nv, Belgium, Director of Bio-IT, previously at GSK.

Professor Steve Kemp, University of Liverpool, UK, Biology.

Dr Mark Wilkinson, U British Columbia, Canada, Bioinformatics, BioMOBY services.

Prof dr Antoine H.C. van Kampen, Netherlands Bioinformatics Centre, Scientific Director, Bioinformatics.

Dr Holger Lausen, SeekDa OG, Austria, Web Service Search company, CTO and Co-Founder of web service discovery and matchmaking company.

Dr Terry Payne, University of Liverpool, UK, Computer Science, specialising in Semantic Web Services.

Dr Steve Pettifer, School of Computer Science, University of Manchester, UK

Feature List for the Pilot

User Registration and Management

User registration and user profiles (for both regular users and service providers).

Service Registration and Management

Single submission of a SOAP service (registered users only).

Batch submission of many SOAP services (registered users only).

Submission of all services from a SOAPLab server (registered users only).

Duplicate checking of SOAP services, during submission.

Ability to preview basic information about a service before submission

Automatic version detection and handling of versioning for SOAP services (based on changes in the WSDL).

Handling of multiple service deployments of the same service (tied into versioning).

View all information about a service in one place, including the different operations, inputs, outputs and all information about these.

Search

Search for services matching some free text.

Browse latest services submitted and last updated services.

Filtering (by category, by provider, by technology)

Annotation

Ability to tag a service with specific keywords (tagging).

Ability to add any information to a service or its parts (as annotations) which then become searchable.

Notification

RSS feeds for the latest services submitted and the last updated services.

Integration with myExperiment

Services from BioCatalogue displayed in myExperiment so users of myExperiment can browse them. This includes a “Latest Services” and “Updated Services” list.

Services within workflows in myExperiment reference the appropriate services in BioCatalogue so users can click through to the information in BioCatalogue.

Meeting Agenda/Minutes

Time : 15:00-17:00 (UK)

Attending

Manchester: Franck

EBI: Eric, Hamish, Rodrigo, Thomas

Apologies

Carole, Jiten, Katy (away at ISMB )

Minuting

Eric

Agenda

Action Items from previous meeting

progress on the interim service to serve EMBRACE etc

progress on the questionnaire

progress on the flyer

progress on the wiki

progress on the mock-ups

progress on the metadata model

review of the timetable (I sent round)

next two face to face meetings (Carole can only do 28-30 July)

Actions from Previous Meeting

Carole - To speak to Steve Petefer about the pilot

Carole/Rodrigo - Schedule an advisery meeting

Rodrigo - To send dates EBI team is available for a Face 2 face meeting

Franck - prepare a questionnaire for ISMB

Khalid - To send more info about 'QASAR' on the mailing list.

Round-table

Upcoming Meetings

ISMB

EBI-Manchester face-2-face

Minutes

Given that it was only Franck participating from Manchester, there was agreement to discuss only ISMB related issues

Agenda Items

Alan and Franck are preparing a BioCatalogue specific flyer for the ISMB meeting. Rodrigo wanted to know if it was possible to have a preview of the flyer before the ISMB. Franck agreed to post the flyer to the mailing list.

Thomas presented mock-ups for some BioCatalogue interfaces(search, browse, register service, register user ).

There has been no feedback yet from Carole on the expanded website content. It is not clear to Thomas if he should go ahead and put the content he has at the moment on the website. Another reminder to be sent to Carole/Katy to comment on the content

No functional material will be shown at ISMB, not even to specific communities like EMBRACE. EMBRACE will do a pre-BioCatalogue as the project requirements warrant them to do something now. They are expecting to adopt the BioCatalogue afterwards( by end of 2008). Several other projects are known to have catalogue related requirements. But there is a discussion to be had as to whether the BioCatalogue will/should cover the scope of all of those projects.

Franck and Eric to agree on a database model, based on the annotation model, with the aim to help the development start as soon as possible. Feedback from ISMB should be used to prioritize development activities

EBI to suggest dates for the face-2-face meeting at EBI. It would be necessary to have 'developer specific' face-2-face meetings as well. This is to be further discussed with the whole team after ISMB.

Action Items

Action EBI : Suggest dates for the face-2-face meeting at EBI

Action Franck : Send flyer and questionnaire to the mailing list before EBI team flies to ISMB on Friday

Action Eric/Franck : Agree on database model for the pilot

Action Thomas : Create individual wiki accounts for the Manchester team

Previous/Next Minutes

Previous meeting: Phone Conference Meeting on Jul 08 2008

Next meeting: Phone Conference Meeting on Jul 22 2008

Meeting Agenda/Minutes

Date: Friday 19th September 2008

Time: 15:00-17:00 (UK)

Attending

Manchester: Jits, Franck

EBI: Eric, Hamish, Rodrigo, Thomas

Apologies

Katy, Carole

Minuting

Franck

Agenda

Action Items from previous meeting

Developement of the pilot

Discussion: Beanshell repository in BioCatalogue

Actions from Previous Meeting

Jits : Add welcome message to the BioCatalogue friends list which is email upon subscription - completed

Thomas : Add the questionnaire to the website Ongoing

EBI/Manchester : Update the wiki with the expectations for F2F at EBI - Compeleted

EBI/Manchester : Use the wiki and mailing list to agree on the MUSTS for the BioCat requirements - completed

Minutes

New Actions

Jits: setup a developper design meeting.

Jits: Speak to Dave about the new privacy policy in myExperiment

Everyone: read EBI privacy policy

Jits/Thomas: discuss UI coordiantion

Eric/Jits: Agree on a date for Eric's visit in Manchester

Pilot BioCatalogue

Eric working on getting SOAP service into the database. He produced something he got Franck to test. He is having problems finding a WSDL parser through API.

Thomas has completed the registration piece using RESTful stuff.

Jits will start working on connecting the work done by Eric from Monday.

Eric is responsible for the DB migrate script/change.

Discussion: Beanshell repository in BioCatalogue: BioCatologue is a registry not a repository so we can not think of Beanshell repostory. However provided that myExperiment has a beanshell repository, BioCatalogue should be able to point to it.

Next Meeting

Upcoming Meetings

Rodrigo is going to the ECCB meeting in Italy. Will try to prevent the EMBRACE team to promote “yet!” another catalogue. That is, he will make sure they mention that BioCatalogue will take over the newly created EMBRACE registry.

AOB

Previous/Next Meetings

Previous meeting: Phone Conference Meeting on Aug 08 2008

Next meeting:

1st December 2009

Previous release revision: 1300

This release revision: 1350

Steps To Take for Update

In order…

Run database update tasks:

rake db:migrate RAILS_ENV=production

Restart the worker(s). For each, do:

ruby script/worker stop
ruby script/worker start

Run the 'search by data script'

ruby script/biocatalogue/import_annotations_io_examples_nov09.rb

Set up a cron job to update annotation properties

rake biocatalogue:submit:update_annotation_properties_full RAILS_ENV=production

Rebuild assets

rake asset:packager:build_all

Restart application instance(s)

Release Notes

Email for the friends' list:

By George:

Hi all

We have just released a brand new "Search by data" feature. It allows
you to query for services that might analyze or process a given real
data. For example, given a Fasta file, it returns a list of services
that possibly consume sequences in Fasta format.

To access the feature go to:
www.biocatalogue.org/search/by_data
or click on a drop-down button just on the right site of "Providers" link.

We would appreciate any suggestions or comments which will help us to
improve this feature.
Note that "Search by data" depends on example inputs and outputs for
service operations in BioCatalogue.
If you add a new service or annotate one, please add example inputs and
outputs to improve the visibility of the service.

Note also that we are logging your queries, which enables us to monitor
and improve the quality on results. We hope to use this data to develop
automatic tools for service annotation in the future. Meanwhile, we
suggest you not to use secure or confidential data while searching for
services.

Regards,

The BioCatalogue Team 

Date: Monday 08th June 2009

Time: 15:00-16:00 (UK)

Telcon No: 08445805588

Pin: 70503011

Attending

Manchester: Jits, Franck, Steve

EBI: Eric

Apologies

Carole, Rodrigo, Thomas

Minuting

Agenda

Actions from the last telcon

Embrace content acquisition

Progress/developement of the beta

progress on service monitoring

Technical meeting

Summary of tasks on Rubyforge

BioCatalogue support review

20 Questions analysis

Actions from Previous Meeting

Franck and Jits to figure out how to use the annotations already existing to generate more useful search terms…ongoing

Eric report on the detailed results of load and throughput testings including peak and average cases…Eric did the test on the BioCatalogue test site…completed

Jits and Franck and Steve: Import content of the Embrace registry…ongoing

Franck - draft the demo…ongoing

* progress on service monitoring The monitoring piece is ready to be deployed on the beta site. Eric to create a simple list to record the history of monitored services.

Minutes

Actions from the last telcon

Franck and Jits working on service categorization. Franck has produced a number of terms to use for that. Franck has updated the myGrid domain ontology. The new ontology will be used to generate pseudo synonyms which can then be used by the search engine (solar) to discover related services. Jits is looking into the last point.

Eric did a load testing on the test site. The result shows that the catalogue can not handle over 4 requests per second.

new release

New update scheduled for Wednesday. We'll first do an update on the test site on Tuesday.

Jits has updated the code base to Ruby on Rails 2.3

New actions

Eric: to ask Ebi system administrator to install 'MEM' cache on the beta site.

Franck: Look at Embrace service category.

Jits: to send instruction on how to use Money cache efficiently

Upcoming Meetings

ISMB

AOB

Previous/Next Meetings

Previous meeting: Phone Conference Meeting on June 03 2009

Next meeting: